NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services, Maria Neira Files. 6174/018
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services, Maria Neira Files
1988-2011
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
Neira, Maria
6174/018
5.5 cubic feet
5.5 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
As vice president of New York State United Teachers, Maria Neira oversees the union's initiatives on educational policy and is NYSUT's frontline advocate to the New York State Board of Regents and the State Education Department. At her direction, the NYSUT Education & Learning Trust, the union's professional development arm, has strengthened and expanded educational opportunities for teachers and other school staff. Neira was appointed by President Obama to serve on the President's Advisory Commission on Educational Excellence for Hispanics. She also serves on the Congressional Hispanic Caucus Institute Advisory Council. She is a member of the National Board for Professional Teaching Standards and the founding publisher of Educator's Voice. An AFT vice president, she also serves as a vice president of the New York State AFL-CIO Executive Council and as a member of the Board of Directors of the AFL-CIO's Workforce Development Institute. She is a member of the New York State Workforce Investment Board, the Greater Capital Region United Way Board of Directors, Capital District's 100 Hispanic Women, the Labor Council for Latin American Advancement and the National Association of Latino Elected Officials Education Fund. She directs NYSUT's fundraising as a statewide flagship sponsor for American Cancer Society programs, including the Making Strides Against Breast Cancer annual walks in which union volunteers have raised millions for the cause. She has served on many state committees, including the governor's Children's Cabinet Advisory Board and the State Committee of Practitioners, and is a member of several other professional organizations. Neira is a recipient of the Ellis Island Medal of Honor from the National Ethnic Coalition of Organizations, the Educational Leadership Award of the National Puerto Rican Day Parade and the YMCA Northeast New York Woman of Achievement Award. She has been honored by the United Federation of Teachers Hispanic Affairs Committee, the Hispanic Latino Cultural Center, Long Island Latino Teachers Association, the Schenectady Hispanic Heritage Committee and the Girl Scouts of Northeastern New York. She previously served as assistant to the president on education issues for the United Federation of Teachers, NYSUT's affiliate in New York City public schools, where she directed a wide range of education initiatives and helped develop strategic plans for education reform. She also served as director of the UFT's Special Educator Support Program. Neira began her teaching career in New York City in 1977 and was a fourth-grade bilingual teacher at the Bilingual Bicultural Mini School in Manhattan. Neira holds a B.A. and an M.S. from Hunter College of the City University of New York.
7544295
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 15, 2011
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 06, 2014
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Biographical / Historical
As vice president of New York State United Teachers, Maria Neira oversees the union's initiatives on educational policy and is NYSUT's frontline advocate to the New York State Board of Regents and the State Education Department. At her direction, the NYSUT Education & Learning Trust, the union's professional development arm, has strengthened and expanded educational opportunities for teachers and other school staff.
Neira was appointed by President Obama to serve on the President's Advisory Commission on Educational Excellence for Hispanics. She also serves on the Congressional Hispanic Caucus Institute Advisory Council. She is a member of the National Board for Professional Teaching Standards and the founding publisher of Educator's Voice.
An AFT vice president, she also serves as a vice president of the New York State AFL-CIO Executive Council and as a member of the Board of Directors of the AFL-CIO's Workforce Development Institute. She is a member of the New York State Workforce Investment Board, the Greater Capital Region United Way Board of Directors, Capital District's 100 Hispanic Women, the Labor Council for Latin American Advancement and the National Association of Latino Elected Officials Education Fund. She directs NYSUT's fundraising as a statewide flagship sponsor for American Cancer Society programs, including the Making Strides Against Breast Cancer annual walks in which union volunteers have raised millions for the cause. She has served on many state committees, including the governor's Children's Cabinet Advisory Board and the State Committee of Practitioners, and is a member of several other professional organizations.
Neira is a recipient of the Ellis Island Medal of Honor from the National Ethnic Coalition of Organizations, the Educational Leadership Award of the National Puerto Rican Day Parade and the YMCA Northeast New York Woman of Achievement Award. She has been honored by the United Federation of Teachers Hispanic Affairs Committee, the Hispanic Latino Cultural Center, Long Island Latino Teachers Association, the Schenectady Hispanic Heritage Committee and the Girl Scouts of Northeastern New York.
Neira previously served as assistant to the president on education issues for the United Federation of Teachers, NYSUT's affiliate in New York City public schools, where she directed a wide range of education initiatives and helped develop strategic plans for education reform. She also served as director of the UFT's Special Educator Support Program. Neira began her teaching career in New York City in 1977 and was a fourth-grade bilingual teacher at the Bilingual Bicultural Mini School in Manhattan.
Neira holds a B.A. and an M.S. from Hunter College of the City University of New York.
Scope and Contents
Covers 2006-2010, with a few folders 1988-1991. In addition to records of NYSUT's Division of Research and Educational Services, which fell under the purview of the First Vice President, the files document the activities of Maria Neira more generally, in her role as a member of the NYSUT Board of Directors, Executive Committee, Cabinet, Officers' Committee, Administrative Committee, NYSUT Policy Council, National Board for Professional Teaching Standards, and the Education and Learning Trust. Meeting agendas and minutes of these entities are heavily featured, as well as speeches and reports prepared by Neira. Minutes and materials of NYSUT's political action arm, VOTE/COPE, and its lobbying group, the Committee of 100, are also included. Topics cover closing the academic achievement gap, credit recovery (attempts to allow students who missed class to make up course credit online, in order to graduate), charter schools, vocational training and other programs for non-college-bound students, and the state response to federal programs under presidents G. W. Bush and Obama, No Child Left Behind and Race to the Top, respectively.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6174/003: NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services Files. 6174/016: NYSUT Vice-President's Office, Maria Neira Files. All other 6174 collections
Teachers' union, New York (State); Neira, M. (Maria); New York State United Teachers; New York State United Teachers. Archives
7544295
- 100 Hispanic Women Gala, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  01/30/09 at 6:30PM in Franklin Plaza. List of guests by table; cover memo to Gala Committee with facilitative details
- 100 Hispanic Women Gala Committee Meeting, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Tuesday, August 18, 2009. Program for second annual gala; committee agenda; list of sponsorship levels; correspondence
- 100 Hispanic Women Third Annual Membership Meeting, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Saturday, April 18, 2009. Agenda for third annual membership meeting; mission statement and list of board of directors; membership application; committee description of Capital District Chapter; April 2009 issue of Latino New York
- 100 HW Annual Meeting, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  04/18/09 at 9:00AM in NYSUT HQ. Drafts 1 and 2 of agenda for annual membership meeting; flyer for annual meeting; memos
- 100 HW Leadership Committee, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  7/23/08 at 6:00PM in Exec. Conf. Rm. 1. Memos with list of committee members, meeting agenda
- 100 Hispanic Invoice for 2008 Gala (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Invoice from NYSUT for printing
- 100 Hispanic Annual Membership Mtg., 2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  6/7/08. Outline of presentation; outline of presentation re Capital District Chapter; memos; CD disk re annual meeting; handwritten notes
- 100 Hispanic Women Capital District Inc. Membership, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Membership application from NYSUT vice president Maria Neira
- 100 Hispanic Women Strategic Planning Forum Guidelines, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Strategic Planning Forum agendas; Strategic Planning Forum Priorities; memos
- NYSUT BOCES Committee Meeting, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  12/11/09 at 10:30AM in NYSUT. Publication re NYS Boards of Cooperative Education (BOCES); brochure; draft discussion paper, "Draft Framework for a New York State High School Exiting Credential," December 11, 2009; agenda for NYSUT BOCES Committee meeting; list of NYSUT committee responsibilities
- BOCES, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  11/24/09 at 1:00PM in Conference Room A. Agenda for NYSUT/BOCES District Superintendent Committee meeting; handwritten note re meeting
- BOCES Teachers Association Meeting, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  11/18/09 at 5:30PM in Western NY NYSUT Office. Text of remarks by NYSUT vice president Maria Neira to ED 3 meeting; newspaper clipping re Regents effort to improve teaching; memos
- BOCES, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  11/11/09 at 3:00PM at Exec. Conf. Rm. 2. Handwritten notes from meeting; list of contact information for 2008- 2011 BOCES Statewide Planning Committee
- BOCES, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  10/27/09. Agenda for NYSUT/BOCES District Superintendent Committee
- BOCES Lobby Day, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  03/04/08 at Empire State Plaza. List of participants; letter reminding NYSUT officers of plans to lobby members of state legislature; related memos
- BOCES Committee Meeting, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  5/10/10 at 10:30AM in NYSUT Conference Center. BOCES Statewide Planning Committee agenda; Report on Special Education (cost containment proposals); draft program for 38th annual NYSUT Conference for BOCES Leadership, October 22-23; list of BOCES local presidents by ED
- BOCES District Superintendent Committee, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  01/27/09 at 12:30PM in Executive Conf. Rm 2. NYSUT/BOCES District Superintendent Committee agenda; list of meeting dates
- Capital Region BOCES Collaboration Day, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  11/19/08 at 9AM. Facilitative correspondence re meeting
- Children's Cabinet Advisory Committee, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Summary of meeting of Governor's Children's Cabinet Advisory Board, August 15, 2007; communication to NYSUT vice president Maria Neira requesting submission of Appointments Questionnaire for possible appointment to advisory committee, with attached NYS Police Application for Confidential Background Investigation; list of Children's Cabinet Advisory Board Members; biographical sketches of members; work group agenda re quality early learning programs, October 30; focus group reports re child care quality rating system; draft standards; materials re quality rating system; press release from Executive Chamber, "Governor Spitzer Encourages Child Health Plus Enrollment to Insure New York's Children," August 9, 2007; report by advisory board, "A Description of New York State Early Learning Programs," August 15; Executive Order establishing the Governor's Children's Cabinet; brochure by National Center for Children in Poverty, Columbia University, "Promoting Effective Early Learning: What Every Policymaker and Educator Should Know," January 2007; document, "Universal Coverage for Children: Framing the Problem for Children's Cabinet," comparing Medicaid with Child Health Plus; related memos
- BOCES Pre-Conference Workshop, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  10/3/08 at 3PM in Gideon Putnam Resort, Saratoga, Springs NY. Flyer announcing BOCES Pre-Conference Workshop re disability awareness
- Oswego Boces, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Reprint request forms and photographs; note of thanks to Maria Neira
- BOCES: The Tech Valley Consortium, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Publication, "Connecting the P-16 Educational System & 21st Century Business Environment," with cover note to Maria Neira
- Children's Cabinet Meeting, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  9/3/09 at 10:30am. Descriptions and goals of Early Childhood Advisory Council workgroup, Subcommittee on Children with Incarcerated Parents, Subcommittee on Child Welfare/Juvenile Justice; New York Times editorials decrying conditions at juvenile detention facilities; policy briefs by New York State Afterschool Network (NYSCAN)
- Children's Cabinet Advisory, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  07/09/09 at 10:30AM in Blue Room, State Capitol. Notice of cancellation
- Tax Cap, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  05/07/08 at 3:30PM in Exec. Conf. Rm 2. Memos re meeting
- Stimulus Meeting, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  02/27/09 at 11AM in Exec. Conf. Rm 1. Memo re meeting
- Healthcare Talking Points, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Talking points on health care, November 7, 2009; press release, "House Passage of Affordable Health Care Is a Victory for All Americans: Statement of Randi Weingarten, President, American Federation of Teachers," November 7, 2009
- Education Finance Research Consortium, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  10/31/08 at 8:30AM in State Museum. Invitation to attend presentation, "Three Reports on K-12 Education in New York State," re property taxes, financial management in charter schools, and variations in teacher contracts
- Property Tax Commission, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  01/15/08 at 9:15AM in Dick's Office. Memo re meeting to discuss NYSUT's role in Property Tax Commission
- The New York State Education Department 2008-2009 Regents Budget Proposal (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Printed document, 2008-2009 Regents Budget Proposal
- Children's Advisory Board, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  06/04/09 at 10:30AM in State Capitol, Blue Room. Agenda; summary of February 26 meeting; briefing for June 4 meeting, focusing on disconnected youth; Progress Report on the Recommendations from the People First Forums, August 2008, re delivery of mental health/ developmental disabilities/alcohol abuse treatment services
- Children's Cabinet Advisory, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  02/26/09 at 10:30AM in Blue Room, State Capitol. Agenda; Presentations by the Subcommittee of the Workgroup on Disconnected Youth, February 26; Preliminary Recommendations to Address the Needs of Children with Incarcerated Parents; Progress Report, Local Implementation of Children's Health Insurance Enrollment Efforts Work Group; list of members of Advisory Board to be appointed to the Early Childhood Advisory Council
- Children's Cabinet, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  7/31/08 at 10:30AM in Blue Room of the Capitol. Memo
- Children's Cabinet, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  July 31, 2008 at 10:30-2:30pm in Blue Room, 2nd Fl Capitol. Agenda; Project Brief for Early Childhood Comprehensive Systems Planning Initiative; talking points re tax cap; related materials
- Children's Cabinet Advisory Bd., 2008 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  05/8/08 at 10:30am in State Capitol, Blue Rm. Universal Pre-K (UPK) Implementation Work Group Report to the Advisory Board, May 8; Early Learning Financing Work Group Report to the Advisory Board, May 8; response to recommendations; budget highlights
- Children's Cabinet, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  02/01/08 at 10:30AM in ESP Concourse Level, Meeting Rm. 6. Meeting notice
- Children's Cabinet Advisory Committee, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  Filled-in appointments questionnaire, authorization for disclosure of protected health information, and application for confidential police background check for NYSUT vice president Maria Neira for appointment to the Children's Cabinet Advisory Committee; Excerpts from the NYS Public Officers Law and other laws and regulation related to Ethics in State Government, from the NYS Ethics Commission; Neira resume
- Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  Letter to Maria Neira from Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies, urging Children's Cabinet to support proposed legislation to aid disconnected youth, December 18, 2008
- Children's Cabinet: Teenage Births, Outcomes for Teen Parents and their Children, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  December 2008 report by Schuyler Center for Analysis and Advocacy, send to Maria Neira in her role as a member of the Children's Cabinet Advisory Board
- Children's Cabinet Quality Stars NY, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  Program for 30th Anniversary Celebration for Center for Women in Government and Civil Society, September 25, 2008; meeting summary for Quality Stars NY webinar; description of Quality Stars NY, a program of the NYS Office of Children and Family Services
- Committee of 100 NYSUT, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  March 23-24, 2009. Agenda for lobby day; tip sheet on effective lobbying; list of members of Assembly and Senate Education Committee, Higher Education Committee, Ways and Means Committee, Finance Committee, with office numbers; note sheets for use after meetings with individual legislators; list of members of NYSUT Legislative Department; briefing sheets re issues of importance to NYSUT (K-12, SUNY, CUNY, retirement, health and safety)
- Committee of 100, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  03/15-16/10. Agenda for lobby day; tip sheet on effective lobbying; list of members of Assembly and Senate Education Committee, Higher Education Committee, Ways and Means Committee, Finance Committee, with office numbers; note sheets for use after meetings with individual legislators; list of members of NYSUT Legislative Department; briefing sheets re issues of importance to NYSUT (K-12, SUNY, CUNY, retirement, health care, charter schools); flyer re teachers centers; letter to legislators in advance of lobby day
- Committee of 100, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  05/11/10. Agenda for lobby day; tip sheet on effective lobbying; list of members of Assembly and Senate Education Committee, Higher Education Committee, Ways and Means Committee, Finance Committee, with office numbers; note sheets for use after meetings with individual legislators; list of members of NYSUT Legislative Department; briefing sheets re issues of importance to NYSUT (K-12, SUNY, CUNY, retirement, health and safety); projected school district job losses, updated May 10, 2010
- NYSUT Committee of 100 Meeting, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  02/03/09 at 10AM in Albany, NY. Agenda for extraordinary meeting of Committee of 100/lobby day; tip sheet on effective lobbying; list of members of Assembly and Senate Education Committee, Higher Education Committee, Ways and Means Committee, Finance Committee, with office numbers; note sheets for use after meetings with individual legislators; list of members of NYSUT Legislative Department; issues briefing sheet
- Committee of 100 Higher Education Lobby Day, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  March 2-3, 2009. Testimony to the Senate Finance Committee on the proposed 2009-10 Executive Budget, prepared by Professional Staff Congress/CUNY, January 15, 2009; agenda for higher education lobby day; tip sheet on effective lobbying; list of members of Assembly and Senate Education Committee, Higher Education Committee, Ways and Means Committee, Finance Committee, with office numbers; note sheets for use after meetings with individual legislators; flyer, Invest in Higher Education
- Committee of 100, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  05/12-13/08. Agenda for lobby day; tip sheet on effective lobbying; list of members of Assembly and Senate Education Committee, Higher Education Committee, Ways and Means Committee, Finance Committee, with office numbers; note sheets for use after meetings with individual legislators; list of members of NYSUT Legislative Department; briefing sheets re issues of importance to NYSUT (K-12, SUNY, CUNY, retirement, health and safety)
- Committee of 100, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  03/17-18/08. Agenda for lobby day; tip sheet on effective lobbying; list of members of Assembly and Senate Education Committee, Higher Education Committee, Ways and Means Committee, Finance Committee, with office numbers; note sheets for use after meetings with individual legislators; list of members of NYSUT Legislative Department; briefing sheets re issues of importance to NYSUT (K-12, SUNY, CUNY), opposition to tax cap
- Committee of 100, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  3/17/08 in Desmond. Agenda for Political Action Committee meeting and lobby day
- Committee of 100, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  05/07-08/07 at 8PM in Desmond Hotel. NYSUT Research Department Contract Language for Peer Review and or Portfolio (actual contract language from various locals); State Education Department Regents Priority Proposal: Adding to the Prospective Pool of Qualified Teachers: Re-Employing Retired Public Employees as Teachers in Hard-to-Staff Schools; working drafts of growth models; materials re tenure decisions; handwritten notes from meeting
- Committee of 100, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 50)